reviewing,
like,
iterating what might be able to
do with it.
This is really good.
Like, if you do a good job at
catching,
like,
and, like, giving students
benefit of the dollar.
Yes.
But we set things up so that,
like,
if there's any ambiguity,
we give you the point rather
than taking it away.
OK, it's 10.30,
so we'll get started.
Good to see everyone again.
A few announcements.
And so first,
if you go to the past exam site,
exams.ease245.org,
you can see our exam and
solutions there.
And as it says on the board,
you will have your grades within
the next 24 hours.
They're actually already ready,
but I need to do some quick spot
checks and reviewing a few
things before getting them out
there.
But you'll have them very soon,
and with them I will update the
grade report so you can see sort
of in one place all of your
scores for everything so far.
And what I will also do is point
you to the
Zoom office hour slots that I've
opened.
I have several today, tomorrow,
next week that you can use if
you want to come and talk about
study strategies or take up
various questions from the exam.
Though, of course, you can come
to regular in-person office
hours for those sorts of things.
In the past, many students have
done this, come to office hours
to talk about how the exam went,
how they studied.
and we can find things that they
may want to do differently.
Homework 5 is going to be
released tomorrow and will be
due next Friday.
And the last thing is I'm trying
something new.
If you go on the course website
and click in class notes,
OK, well, it's not going to open
on my iPad.
But if you do that,
what it should show you is a
live version of what I'm writing
on my iPad, just delayed by like
10 seconds or something.
And so I've often noticed that
I'm like, I finished writing
something and I switched to a
new slide, but people still
wanted to see what was on the
previous slide.
So this should be a way that you
can do that live in lecture.
And then afterwards, I will
still just replace it with the
regular PDF.
OK,
so test that out.
Let me know how well it works.
The plan for today is to recap
very briefly what the last thing
we covered before going into the
midterm was,
before spending the entirety of
our time today discussing
the basics of matrices.
So addition and scalar
multiplication that should sound
familiar How to multiply a
matrix by a vector which is a
special case of how to multiply
a matrix by another matrix Okay,
and these will be the
foundations that we will use in
homework five and build upon for
the rest of the semester
Okay.
So what I wanted to answer is
What's the point why do we need
to introduce is the concept of a
matrix.
We've already studied quite a
bit of linear algebra.
In a standard linear algebra
course,
lots of things that we've
already discussed would have
come up later in the semester
once they already talked about
matrices,
things like the span of vectors,
and linear independence,
and basis,
and dimension.
These are all things you already
understand, and we've done them
relatively early in the
semester.
And the idea of a matrix in a
regular linear algebra They
probably talk about it on the
first day or two.
You know, we're a month into the
class and still haven't talked
about matrices.
Why are we now needing to talk
about them if we could do so
much without them?
And the short answer is because
I want to use them to solve one
very specific problem.
So this should be blue.
Suppose I have a vector v.
And down here, actually,
sorry I should have called that
u not that it really matters but
let's suppose I have some vector
u in RN
and I have some vectors v1
v2 and so on also in rn,
all the way through vd.
The question I want to be able
to answer is,
which vector in the span
of all of these v's
is closest to the vector u.
Ultimately,
everything we are about to do
for the next two weeks is going
to help us answer this question.
I have a collection of vectors
in Rn, v1 through vd.
Their span is some subspace of
what?
Their span, which is this sort
of plain looking thing I've
drawn, it's a subspace of what?
Subspace of R what?
Rn,
good, because the vectors all
live in Rn.
There are just d of them.
Their span is some subspace of
Rn.
The question I want to try and
answer is,
you,
let's suppose it's not in the
subspace, necessarily.
It's in Rn, but it's not
necessarily in the span of the
v's.
The question is,
how do I find the vector in the
subspace that is closest to you,
okay? Why do I want to answer
that?
Well it's because if we can
answer this then we have all of
the tools we need to return to
the multiple linear regression
problem of finding optimal model
parameters that allow us to make
predictions for a linear
regression model that has
multiple input variables, okay?
And this is the final piece of
the puzzle figuring out how to
find the vector in a subspace
closest to some other vector
that's not necessarily in this
subspace.
And you can imagine this has
connections to things we've
already studied.
We've already studied a simpler
case of this,
which is if there's just only
one v vector.
Because if there's only one v,
then a span of v is a line, and
we've learned how to project u
onto v.
That was on the midterm, and we
studied that quite a bit.
But now this is a more broad
question,
because we don't have just one
vector v.
We have multiple v's, and their
span isn't just a line.
and, rather, it's some more
general subspace.
And the question we're trying to
answer is,
well, among all of the vectors
in that subspace, which one is
closest to you?
That's what we're trying to
understand.
And the short answer is,
to answer,
we need matrices.
Sound OK?
All right.
Now, geometrically, you can
probably guess how we will
arrive at the answer or once we
know about matrices,
visually,
what vector in this subspace do
you think is closest to you?
If you had to extend things
we've already discussed.
Among all vectors in this
subspace, which I've sort of
drawn like this plane,
which vector in there do you
think is closest to you? What
property will that have?
Yeah, Paul.
V1?
Well,
V1 and V2 are not the only
vectors in the subspace.
Here I've drawn them as vectors
that are spanning the subspace.
But the subspace has infinitely
many vectors in them.
I'm not looking for just V1 or
V2 necessarily.
V1 looks closer than V2,
yes.
But I guess I'm asking more
generally,
which vector in that entire
subspace is closest to you?
What property would that closest
vector have?
Would it be like projection on
one of the V1s?
Well, you're on the right track,
but it's not about the
projection onto any one of these
necessarily.
How about this? Let me redraw
the picture because I think the
way that I happened to place the
V1 and V2 is leading to a little
confusion.
The problem is,
the hypothetical problem is the
same because this V1 and V2,
their is still that same
subspace.
Now I'm asking, among every
vector in that subspace, of
which there are infinitely many,
it's not just two,
right?
That subspace is made up of all
linear combinations of v1 and
v2,
or also including v3 and so on.
There's infinitely many vectors
in this collection.
Which one is closest to you?
Projection of u onto v1.
Exactly, it's the projection of
u onto the subspace, and what
property would that projection
have?
What property would that
projection have?
It would be a linear combination
of v1 and v2.
Yeah, it would be a linear
combination of all of the v's.
In this picture, I just have v1
and v2.
But in general, I would have
more.
And what geometric property
would that projection have?
Yeah?
Close.
It's not that the projection
would be perpendicular, but it's
that its error would be
perpendicular.
So the projection would just be
some vector in this subspace,
which is some linear combination
of v1 and v2 and the other v's.
And the property it would have
is that its error would be
perpendicular to the subspace.
But to be able to find what that
optimal linear combination of
the v vectors is,
we need a few tools that are
most conveniently described of
using matrices.
So are we clear on what I mean
by what is the closest vector in
the subspace?
The answer is not v1 or v2 or
any one of the v's themselves.
It's some linear combination of
the v's.
Yeah?
I don't know if I'm
misunderstanding, but what if
there's another vector that
isn't perpendicular but is
physically closer to you?
There isn't.
It's the same logic we used when
we learned that the orthogonal
projection was the closest
vector along v
to u.
We used the Pythagorean theorem
to prove that.
You could apply the same logic
here.
If there was some vector that
you thought was closer,
like I don't know,
this vector,
well then it's sort of hard to
see here, but you could draw a
little triangle here.
And that other vector's error
vector would be a hypotenuse on
a right angle triangle where the
length of this perpendicular
error vector is shorter.
And again, this is just a
preview of where we're going.
We're going to cover this in
more depth in a couple of weeks
after fall break.
Sound good?
But anyways, this is where we're
going, and we need matrices to
get there.
So what is a matrix?
I defined a vector as being an
ordered list of numbers.
think of a matrix as a
rectangular array of
numbers.
The letter I will use, or the
sort of notation I will use for
matrices is I will refer to them
by capital letters, no arrow hat
on top.
And we will use square brackets
like we did for vectors.
So I'm just going to use the
same example I've used in the
notes here for our first vector.
3, 2, 0, 2 is its first column,
1, 1, negative 1,
negative 2 is its second column,
and 4, 9, 0, 0 is its third
column.
Now, this matrix has four rows
and three columns.
And the default interpretation I
want you to have when you look
at a matrix immediately is that
you should just think of it as
being a collection of vectors
written next to each other.
OK, so you can imagine this is
like the vector A1,
this is the vector A2,
maybe this is the vector A3,
OK?
But there are two
interpretations.
I can think of this as three
vectors in R4,
or what else could I think of
this as? And this relates to a
question that was in homework
four.
Four vectors in R3? Yeah, just
as well.
I can think of this as four
vectors in R3.
OK, great.
So this matrix is four rows and
three columns.
So the way that I would describe
its shape
is four by three.
And this is how I pronounce
that.
4 by 3.
And I might say that this matrix
is in the set R 4
by 3,
which you can think of as the
set of all 4 by 3 matrices whose
components are real numbers,
OK?
Rows by columns.
Another piece of notation here
just to be aware of,
sometimes if we have a matrix,
next to it we may write the
subscripts i,
j,
and sometimes we'll use
uppercase letters, sometimes
we'll use lowercase letters.
All this is referring to is the
element
at row I,
column J.
So whenever referring to
matrices,
we always index through the rows
first and then the columns,
OK?
So for example,
let's just save some space here.
Also,
that's what makes it a little
tricky to call these columns A1,
A2, A3.
Because here, like I said,
in this notation,
you refer to a row and then
column,
but then this is column one.
But I called it A1, which is a
little confusing.
So we didn't really need to name
these things, so I'm just not
going to.
And you'll see later on, I will
come up with a different
notation in general for
referring to a column of a
matrix when we need to when we
get back to linear regression.
But anyways, ignore what I just
said for the last 10 seconds.
tell me, what is A23?
Or you should read this as A row
two, column three.
What is that?
Yeah?
Nine.
Nine, good.
One indexed,
just like all of math has been
so.
OK,
so anyways, your default
interpretation should be,
I'm looking at three vectors in
R4 here.
I should think of this as column
vectors written next to each
other.
That's the interpretation we
will use more, but they're also
row vectors written on top of
each other.
And I'll talk a little bit more
about what a row vector is in
just a second.
So the kind of thing we're going
to learn to do next week is ask
questions like, well, what is
the span of the columns of A?
Here, the span of the columns of
A is a subspace of what
universe?
The span of the columns of A
here is a subspace of what?
R4, good, because the columns of
A are in R4.
And then another question I can
ask is, what is the span of the
rows of A?
That's a subspace of what?
Yeah, R3.
OK,
and it turns out that there are
relationships between these
subspaces.
OK,
the cool fact, which I was going
to say for Tuesday, but I'll
tell it to you now so you
marinate on it,
is that for every matrix,
the dimension of the span of the
columns is always equal to the
dimension of the span of the
rows.
Okay,
which is doesn't it like there's
no reason to think that that's
how it would work coming into
this but it happens to be true
Okay
Again that's just a preview of
what's to come.
We'll talk more about that in
just a bit So anyways here, this
is a matrix.
That is four rows by three
columns in general So,
n has been
the placeholder I've used for
the number of things in a
vector,
and so it'll be the placeholder
I use for the number of rows in
a matrix.
D will be the placeholder I use
for the number of columns in a
matrix,
okay? OK,
so based on n and d, which are
the matrix's shape,
I'm not going to call it the
matrix's dimensions because
dimension has a very specific
meaning.
It's the number of vectors in a
basis for a subspace.
So to avoid confusing it with
that word, I'm going to call it
the shape,
OK?
A matrix who has more rows than
columns,
we often call a tall matrix.
A matrix who has more columns
than rows, we call a
wide matrix.
And a matrix who has an equal
number of rows and columns,
what do you think we call it?
A square matrix, okay good.
Now as we will see throughout
the semester,
square matrices are special and
there are a lot of things that
really only apply to square
matrices.
But everything we do today will
apply to matrices in general.
And sometimes non-square
matrices are called rectangular.
Okay,
now if you want to think in the
context of collecting real data
in which,
suppose I ran a survey or in
general just collected some
features about various
individuals and had one row per
data point and one column per
feature, what type of matrix do
you think that information would
be stored in? A tall matrix, a
wide matrix, or a square matrix?
You've got to guess.
Like real data that are
typically
stored in a wide, tall, or
square matrix.
What do you think?
Yeah?
I would say definitely tall.
You probably would have a lot of
data points and not that many
columns.
Exactly.
Usually, data that comes from
measuring some real world thing
is tall in that we have lots of
data points where n is the
number of data points we have.
That is the same placeholder I
use for the number of data
points in a data set when we
were doing simple linear
regression and the constant
model.
And maybe not as many different
measurements per data point.
Okay, so that means real data
often is stored in a tall
matrix.
Okay,
one little thing I want to
remark on rows versus columns.
What I'm writing here,
174.
Therefore,
this is a vector in R3.
It is also a matrix
with shape 3 by 1.
These are the same thing.
Sound reasonable? A vector is
just a special case of a matrix.
Now, what about this creature?
It has the same three numbers,
1, 7, and 4,
but they are written sideways
rather than on top of each
other.
This is a matrix with shape
what?
It's number of rows by number of
columns.
What would we say the shape of
this thing is?
Yeah,
1 by 3.
I'm not going to say this is a
vector in R3.
Okay, vectors in R3 and general
vectors in Rn by convention in
our class will refer to column
vectors.
Okay,
so if I wanted to refer to this
I would just say it's a 1 by 3
matrix or I might call it a row
vector
not
a vector in R3.
Okay, so 174 is a column vector
and 174 is a row vector.
Those are distinct quantities.
I mean the are the same,
but there are different objects
mathematically.
Sound OK?
And at the end of today, I'll
try and show you this operation
that we can apply to a column
vector to turn it into a row
vector and vice versa.
But that'll also be defined more
generally in terms of matrices
as well.
It's not just about vectors.
OK,
so we know what a matrix is.
You can think of it as just like
an extension of vectors, where
it's like a vector of vectors.
It's a vector made up of column
vectors,
OK?
What are the operations this new
object needs to support?
Well, it supports addition and
scalar multiplication,
which works exactly the same way
you would think it does.
So let's suppose I have the same
example A from before.
3,
1, 4,
2, 1, 9,
0, negative 1, 0,
2, negative 2, 0.
By the way, and for what we're
about to do on the next page,
this will become a little more
important.
I like to sometimes write the
shape of a matrix in the bottom
right corner just so I can keep
track of what operations are
allowed.
OK?
For addition and scalar
multiplication, In addition,
what do you think the shape of B
must be in order to add A and B,
let's say?
What do you think the shape of B
must be?
So what then?
Yeah,
the shape of B needs to be the
same as the shape of A,
OK,
in order for you to be able to
add matrices,
OK?
And that's because the way you
add is element-wise, the same
way you added vectors,
OK? So imagine, let's just keep
B simple,
1, 2, 3,
4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9,
10,
11, 12,
a valid operation is something
like 3 times A minus B.
That'll give me a new matrix
whose shape is also 4 by 3,
whose elements will come from
taking 3 times an element in A
minus the corresponding element
in B.
Okay, we don't need to sit here
doing all of these, But,
why don't you tell me the
element at position 1 comma 3,
row 1 column 3.
What's that going to be?
Anyone know?
Yeah, Chris.
9.
Good.
How'd you get that?
Times 3 minus 3.
Good.
4 times 3 minus 3 gives you 9.
And let's just do one more.
So what about the element at
position 3 comma 2?
What do we get there?
Negative 11.
And you got that by doing
negative 1 times 3, which is
negative 3 minus 8, which gives
you negative 11.
OK.
That much is pretty
straightforward.
What's about to happen for the
rest of today is not really as
straightforward as this.
Okay, because matrix
multiplication does not really
work the way that you would
expect it to.
Okay,
that like if you had to guess
based on this slide, how do you
multiply matrices A and B,
one would probably think,
oh, you just do 3 times 1, that
gives you 3, and 1 times 2, that
gives you 2, and 4 times 3 gives
you 12, and 2 times 4 gives you
8.
Okay, you multiply the
corresponding element.
That's not matrix
multiplication.
Okay, that is not matrix
Unfortunately, it's more
complicated than that.
But the reason it is defined the
way it is
will become clear over the next
few lectures because the very
specific definition of matrix
multiplication unlocks lots of
cool properties.
So before we do the
multiplication,
what I want to introduce is what
I sometimes call,
and this is how I've written in
the notes,
the golden rule for matrix
multiplication.
OK.
Here's what it says.
In order to multiply
AB,
here's the rule.
The number of columns in A has
to equal the
number of rows
in B.
Again,
it's hard to predict that this
is what was coming.
So let me move this down a
little.
Why don't we say A
has
shape?
n by d, which has been our
default shape.
Based on this rule,
what must the shape of B be?
If I need the number of columns
in A to equal the number of rows
in B,
what does the shape of B need to
be?
D by something, right?
It doesn't say that the number
of columns in B needs to be
anything,
It's the number of rows in B
needs to be equal to D.
Okay,
so D
has to be the number of rows of
B and the number of columns of B
can be some other thing.
Let's call it P.
Okay,
this is the key here
These
The number of columns in A,
which is D The first thing I've
highlighted and the number of
rows in B, the second thing I've
highlighted,
those are sometimes called
The inner dimensions.
OK, why is it the inner
dimensions? Well, it's when you
write n by d next to d by p,
the two d's are next to each
other.
They're the inside of the pair
of the dimensions.
Whereas the outer dimensions
would be what?
What would the outer dimensions
be?
Outer dimensions?
Yeah, in this specific case, if
the inner dimensions are D and
D, what are the outer
dimensions?
N and P.
So,
the product AB
has G.
N by P.
So those outer dimensions
matter.
It's because they tell you the
number of rows in the product
and the number of columns in the
product.
So you can think of the inner
dimensions as collapsing or
canceling each other out.
So far you have no reason to
know why this definition is
needed or why this golden rule
is needed.
So let me convey this to you by
way of an example.
So let's start with the simplest
case,
which is where the second matrix
is
actually just a vector,
has one column.
Once we learn how to do that
operation, then we can extend it
to the case where the second
matrix actually has multiple
columns.
So let me bring over the same A
that I've used a few times here.
Now I can write it out.
3, 1, 4,
2, 1, 9,
0, negative 1, 0,
negative 2,
negative 2, 0.
OK.
Let's suppose I want to multiply
it by a vector.
I could call it whatever.
I want to just call it x for
now.
Before telling you what x is,
just based on what I've written
already, you can tell me what
the shape of x must be.
How many elements must x have?
There's only one answer to this.
What is it?
How many things must x have in
it?
Yeah,
three.
And that's because a is 4 by 3,
and that golden rule said that
the thing you multiply a by has
to be 3 by something.
Okay?
So that means x must be a vector
with three things in it,
and for my example, I'll use 1,
0, 3.
So here this is 3 by 1.
The golden rule said these inner
dimensions have to be the same
thing.
So x here is a vector in R3.
Okay,
how do you actually multiply A
with x?
Here's what I'm do.
I'm gonna work it out but I'm
not gonna explain what I'm
doing.
I'm just gonna do it and then
I'm gonna give you a little bit
of time and I want you to
discuss with the people near you
the various ways of interpreting
the calculation I just did.
There are two important
interpretations that are going
on here,
okay?
But first, let me just write it
up.
I just wanted to make this a
little smaller.
Okay.
OK,
check this out.
And in usual fashion, I'm going
to add some colors to this.
Let's do 1,
0,
3.
All right, here we go.
I'll sit down.
Halfway
there.
Okay.
There are two ways to interpret
the calculation I just did.
Firstly,
what is this shape? I
intentionally didn't simplify
here.
The result, whatever.
I can tell you what it ends up
being, but the specific number
is not important.
It's 15, 29,
0, 2, which is a vector with how
many things in it?
Four.
And you can think of that as a
four by one matrix.
And I could have predicted that
that was what was going to come
out based on what I said on the
last slide.
I said, when the inner
dimensions match,
then it's legal to multiply, and
the result has the outer
dimensions, which are four by
one.
So you knew I was going to give
you a vector with four things in
it.
You didn't know that this is
what I was going to do.
OK, so discuss with the people
near you for a minute.
How can you interpret the
calculation I just did? There
are two ways you can interpret
it.
One is slightly more obvious.
One is more subtle.
Oh,
you're just summing that one up.
Summing that one up.
Each column gets multiplied in
alternating order.
The first column gets multiplied
by the first element.
Everything on the second column
gets multiplied by the first
element.
It has to be in the same
interdimensional form.
Yeah, we can also talk something
about linear combinations.
They have to be like,
yeah.
They have to be the same.
So you just do first row times
first column.
Oh, first.
And then you do first row,
second column, first column.
times one one plus
I've
seen the way going
across the road
OK,
two ways to interpret what's
going on here.
Give me one way.
What did you discover?
What did you discover? Yeah?
I just said,
since there's the same number of
elements in the vector,
there is columns in the matrix.
You multiply the first column in
the matrix by the first number
in the vector, and then the
second column by the second
number, and so on.
OK.
So you did it.
That was the more subtle
interpretation, and actually the
more important interpretation.
But that's absolutely right.
So what you just described is
that the output is a linear
combination of A's columns.
OK,
good.
You know what?
Let me,
yeah, OK.
Let me write that down second,
just because in the notes it
comes second.
And I don't expect people to
think of that when I first posed
this.
But that's the more important
interpretation.
What was the other
interpretation you saw?
So indeed, yes, this is a linear
combination of A's columns.
What else was going on? of x and
then the rows.
Good.
That's the other interpretation
I was looking for.
All we're doing here is taking a
dot product of x
with every one of a's rows.
Try and paste this.
There we go.
So I think, Alex, you were doing
this sort of visual, which I
also think about.
The way you can think about this
is you can pretend your x here,
you rotate yourself,
so you have the 1 here,
the 0 here,
and the 3 here.
And you can imagine x hitting
this vector and getting dot
producted with it.
And that's what comes out here.
3 times 1, plus 0 times 1,
plus 3 times 4.
Okay?
And then x comes and hits this
vector.
Gets dot producted with it,
and you get the dot product of
103 with 219.
Then x comes and hits this
vector, and you get the dot
product of 103 with 0, negative
1, 0.
and so on.
So you can imagine the vector
being rotated and then sliding
down the rows and computing all
of these dot products.
Do we agree?
OK,
now there's one subtlety with
this,
which is that it's not exactly a
dot product or it's a dot
product with a caveat,
which is that the dot product is
only defined between two vectors
in Rn,
but I just told you that row
vectors are not thought of as
vectors in Rn.
So it's a dot product if you
think of the row vectors as
regular vectors,
okay? It's sort of like a
pedantic point, but an important
one to state here.
Okay,
but in any case that's
interpretation one.
Awesome.
A X contains
the dot products of
X with A's rows if
you think of
them as vectors in R3,
okay?
Now,
why does this tell us,
like,
okay, knowing that this is how
the calculation works,
where did our golden rule come
from?
The golden rule, remember, said
the number of columns in A had
to be equal to the number of
rows in X.
Why like what does this
calculation here tell us about
that golden rule?
Yeah
Like to do the dot product
between like two vectors they
have to have the same number of
elements Exactly because we're
taking the dot products of X
with the rows of a it needed to
be legal to do that dot product
Which requires that the rows of
a have the same number of things
in them that X does But each row
of A, how many things does it
have?
It has one thing per column of
A, which is why the condition is
about the number of columns in
A.
And just so it's highlighted
here,
this is one dot product.
And this is another dot product.
So this dot product
interpretation
is the one you will use if I
ever ask you, or when I ask you,
to multiply a matrix by a vector
or a matrix by another matrix.
Okay, you're not gonna do a ton
of these calculations by hand,
but you still need to know how
to do them.
And this is the one that's
quicker for actually just
calculating a result.
Sound okay?
Alright,
so that's the first
interpretation.
The second is
more conceptually important.
Let's take a look at what
happened here.
What you might have noticed,
and I can move this over a
little.
is that every entry in A's first
column
was multiplied by the number 1.
And every entry in A's second
column was multiplied by the
number 0.
And every entry in A's third
column, 4900, was multiplied by
the number 3.
So really,
multiplying a by x was creating
a linear combination of a's
columns.
And what was that linear
combination?
It was 1 times the first column,
plus 0 times the second column,
plus 3 times the third column.
If you want to see that written
out,
here's how I would think about
it.
Let me make this a little
smaller.
I forgot to copy it all.
This looks something like 1
times
3,
2, 0, negative 2
plus 0 times 1,
1, negative 1, negative 2 plus
3.
times 4900.
And the output is still the same
as before.
I'm not saying that this gives
you a different number,
152902.
It's the same result.
It's just another way of
thinking about how the result
came to be.
So today, and moving forward for
the rest of your life, because
matrix multiplication comes up a
lot,
whenever you see this
calculation or you need to think
about this calculation,
I don't want you to think of it
as just some random pattern.
I want you to think of it in
these two ways.
It contains the dot products of
the vector x with the rows of A.
Or more importantly,
it contains a linear combination
of A's columns where the
coefficients came from x.
OK.
So any time you see Ax,
you should think what I'm
looking at is a linear
combination of A's columns with
the coefficients from x.
OK.
So like I said, one of the
things I said at the start of
lecture was,
next week we're going to explore
Or,
what is the span of A's columns?
What is that asking? Well, it's
asking,
what is the complete set of
linear combinations of A's
columns?
Like, using A's columns, what
can I make?
But now, knowing that A times x
is just a linear combination of
A's columns,
that's the same as asking,
what are all possible things I
can make using A times x? Like,
what are all possible outputs of
Ax? matrix.
That's the same as asking, what
is the span of A's columns?
So this product of matrix times
vector is one that we're going
to look at a lot today and
moving forward.
Sound OK?
So that was one case,
matrix times vector.
But what I need to eventually
show you how to do is multiply a
matrix by a matrix.
And to illustrate how we do
that, I'm going to use the same
example A matrix
that we've been using,
3, 1, 4.
Actually, before I do that,
there's a cool animation I added
to the notes that I wanted to
show you here.
If you go to 5.1,
scroll down.
I made this for my other class,
and I said, you know what?
We can add it here, too.
I've seen various animations
online,
where if you like,
it's a website where if you
scroll through it, different
things get animated.
So that's how this works.
If you scroll here,
it updates the visual.
So the question is, well, what
is the result of multiplying A
by V here?
The shapes match.
This is not the same example as
the one we looked at before.
Here we have a 2 by 3 matrix A
and a 3 by 1 vector V.
The first interpretation
involves taking these dot
products, so the dot product of
A's first row with V is 26.
With the second row, it's 11.
It happened to be my birthday,
November 26.
But then there's the other
interpretation, which you can
get by scrolling through again.
2 gets multiplied by the first
column.
Negative 1 gets multiplied by
the second column.
3 gets multiplied into the third
column.
And then you see the other way
of getting at that 26 element.
So this is a cool thing I think
you can click through
if you want a refresher or more
a visual intuition of what's
going on here.
OK,
so that was matrix vector.
We're back to matrix times
matrix.
And again,
I'm sticking with the same
by 3 matrix A that we've worked
with.
And B,
it's going to look a little
familiar.
What is familiar about B?
Yeah?
It has three rows.
That's true, but I more mean the
numbers in B specifically.
They're related to the numbers
we use in something else,
like two minutes ago.
Yeah.
It means x.
Yeah, its first column is the
same vector x we saw before,
which indeed has three rows.
So this is the same as x we saw
before.
Now, the golden rule says I can
multiply these.
Why?
Well, it's because b has three
rows, which is the same as the
number of columns in a,
and has two columns.
What does that tell me the shape
of this result is going to be?
The resulting matrix, what's its
shape going to be?
Yeah, go for it.
Four by two.
It's gonna have four rows and
two columns.
Now this is a good place to stop
and do attendance.
We'll give us a little break.
It's 11 16.
We'll start at 11 20.
But once you figure out
attendance and
get water or whatever,
what I want you to think about
is how do you think we multiply
A by B? And why did I point out
the fact that B,
this first column, is something
we've already seen?
I have many exams.
You can do that in the case of a
plane.
That's definitely true.
I think that would have
something to do with the nail
painting.
Oh,
yeah.
I think what's kind
of confusing is that you've
drawn these vectors this is
where it's indeed.
And here,
we're asking about which factor
the span is closest to each
other.
In this picture,
the answer would just be you,
because I didn't know which
would be,
like, where did you get the V.
In this picture,
I know for sure there's
something V1 plus something V2
that makes it exact,
because these are two vectors in
the middle.
Notice that I have to use it for
another assignment that also
tests stuff too.
The concept doesn't really make
sense in that
picture, so I'm going to ask
them about the test cases.
Because I can see higher
dimensions.
Imagine I have some v1,
some v2,
and this plane,
I think of them as a span,
instead
You should think of a you that
isn't on this, so there's no way
to make it on this band.
The question is,
among everything in this band,
which is close to me,
does not necessarily v1 or v2.
I wouldn't necessarily draw it
that way,
but whatever it is, it's the one
supplicant.
Pretend the answer is the
vector.
It's whatever vector has an
error that's perpendicular to
it, which is the same idea we
used when doing the projection
of 4.
Before, when we had some user
view.
Okay, well, we want to project
it onto V.
We wanted to find the vector in
the direction of V.
What was our conclusion?
Our conclusion was the answer.
You can think of it as being
perpendicular to every
possible linear combination of
vectors.
Like any vector who lives on the
plane,
this error is perpendicular to
the plane.
I meant to make the same one on
three, but it applies.
So yeah,
what this requires you to think
about is what does it end for a
vector to be perpendicular to a
subspace of r sub.
But it's sort of a
generalization of this concept.
This p isn't made up by just
multiplying one vector,
it's made up by multiplying lots
of vectors by different numbers.
I don't have any more after
this.
I think that I could do a lot of
questions in 280.
My name's really just Brian.
OK.
I'll touch a book with you,
man.
So that was a good answer.
The question I left you with
was, how do you think we
multiply A by B, where A is the
same matrix we saw before,
and B has two columns,
the first of which we've seen
before? If you have to guess,
how do you think this operation
works?
Yeah?
I was just saying that's the one
we got in the previous column
and then the second column B,
the linear combination of the
second column of B.
Exactly.
All that you need to do to
multiply a matrix by another
matrix is to repeatedly multiply
the first matrix by the columns
of the second one.
That's why I use these specific
examples.
we already multiplied A by the
column vector 1, 0, 3.
Those numbers were 15,
29,
0, and 2.
This is the same as last
example.
The next column is going to come
from multiplying 3, 1, 4,
2, 1, 9,
0, negative 1, 0, and 2,
negative 2, 0 by 2,
We don't need to do every single
product there.
But let's do the first and the
third.
Can you tell me what the first
element in this new column is
going to be?
Yeah?
21.
How'd you get that?
It's 6 plus 7 plus 8, which is
the same as 7 plus 7 plus 7,
which is 20.
And what about the third thing?
I got negative 7.
Negative 7, good, because we
have two zeros here.
So the only thing that is
non-zero is 7 times negative 1,
which is negative 7, good.
OK.
Are we clear on where 21 and
negative 7 came from?
OK.
So what I'll say is,
in general,
maybe I'll put this in a
different color.
In general,
column J of AB is equal to A
multiplied
by column J of B.
Yeah? Just for note's sake,
you extend the black line to the
yellow.
It's the same in the last
example.
Because it looks similar.
Oh, yes, yes, yes, good call,
good call.
Thank you.
Thanks.
No, thank you.
OK, awesome.
OK, are we comfortable on how to
multiply two matrices now?
Okay,
now there's something sort of
tangential that I want to talk
about, which is about
the runtime complexity of this
operation.
For simplicity,
let's suppose A is n by n and B
is also n by n.
Their product is than also an n
by n matrix.
How many operations
does
it take
to multiply AB?
What I'm looking for is like a
280 or 281 style answer to what
is the complexity of the matrix
multiplication operation.
How many operations does this
require as a function of n?
Yeah, Alex.
I'm totally guessing, but is it
n squared?
Where did you get n squared
from? Because you have to go
through each column, which would
be n.
But then you also go through
each row, which is also n.
So that would be like, I think,
n times n.
Well, the thing is, you have to
go through each row
of A,
each column of B.
And when you do that, there are
still n calculations, because
the dot product itself requires
n little multiplications and
then adding them up.
So it's n squared dot products,
because you're dotting every row
of A with every column of B.
There's n squared dot products.
And each dot product requires n
operations.
So what's the total runtime
complexity?
n cubed.
Do you have a question?
No?
OK.
n cubed.
n squared dot products,
each requires
n operations.
So I'll call this a big O of n
cubed operation.
You didn't think you were going
to learn about this here today,
did you?
But this is the naive
implementation
of matrix multiplication.
There are quicker ways of doing
it.
And this is like an active area
of research in math.
Can you come up with algorithms
for multiplying two matrices
quicker than n cubed?
And until two days ago,
the quickest algorithm,
until two days ago.
The best known in research was
something like
n to the 2.37.
Then two days ago,
OpenAI,
you may have heard about this
online,
released, and I added this to
the notes already,
but you may have heard OpenAI,
again the creators of ChatGPT,
released this big GitHub repo
with solutions to 700 open
problems in math.
And one of the results that they
have in there
is literally about this exact
thing, which is the big O
complexity for multiplying two
matrices.
And their new discovery is that
they were able to improve on the
previous best known bound,
which was,
I think this will say what the
old one was.
I'm pretty sure it was 2.37.
And they were able to find that
it's possible to do it in O of n
to the 2.25.
And you can take a look at this
if you want.
I mean, most of it doesn't make
sense to me.
But you can look at it.
And this is freely available.
If you just go to github.com
slash openai slash math,
funnily named repo,
you can find this.
Yeah, anonymous commit.
What you'll see is that this is
an existence proof.
It doesn't tell you how to do
it, it just tells you that
theoretically it has to be
possible to be able to do this,
okay?
But anyways, my point in
bringing this up is that one,
it's just very relevant right
now,
and two, this idea of like
finding quicker ways of
multiplying matrices is a very
active area of math research,
which I thought was interesting
given that we happen to be
covering it today.
Okay, so take a look at this if
you're interested, and you know
what, That's interesting enough
that I'll put a screenshot in
the notes.
OK.
All right.
So what I want to talk about now
are some of the properties that
matrix multiplication obeys.
What is the name for the
property I'm about to write?
Yeah, yeah, it's associative.
What that means is if you're
taking the product of three
matrices it doesn't matter which
two you do first.
And matrix multiplication does
have this property.
It is associative.
What is the name for this
property?
And it does have this property.
Yeah, distributive, good.
Now in the context,
like if you pretend one of the
matrices is a vector, this means
two different things, both of
which are true.
It means that like A plus B
times the vector V is equal to
AV plus BV.
That's true.
And it also means A times the
vector sum u plus v is equal to
a u plus a v.
Both of those are true because
they're just special cases of
the statement I've just written.
Okay.
Here's the big one.
It is not commutative.
So in general,
a b is not equal to b a.
This is huge because it is one
of the first times you've
encountered a form of
multiplication that isn't
commutative.
Someone actually submitted a
note to update something in the
notes where I said this is the
first time you've seen
multiplication like this but the
cross product is also not
commutative because if you
reverse the and makes the other
vector negative.
So u cross v is the same as
negative v cross u.
But as we're seeing with AB and
BA,
they're totally different.
And most often,
if you can multiply AB,
it isn't even guaranteed that
you can multiply BA.
And that's a consequence of our
golden rule.
Okay, so suppose A is N by D,
and B is D by P,
AB is a valid product,
because those inner dimensions
match.
But what about BA?
Note that this is asking for a
fundamentally different thing.
AB is asking for linear
combinations of A's columns.
BA would be asking for linear
combinations of B's columns.
There's no reason to think that
these would need to end up being
the same.
But even if we just look at the
dimensions,
sorry, the shapes,
B is D by P,
and A is N by D.
And no one required p, which is
the number of columns of b,
and n, which is the number of
rows of a,
to be the same.
So this product, ba, is only
valid if n is equal to p.
So the first thing to note is
that just because ab is
valid,
BA doesn't have to be.
Now typically at this point I
ask,
okay so what for what kind of
matrix do for what kind of
matrices I should say are both
AB and BA valid?
And the answer you're probably
thinking of is well if they're
both square then you could do it
both ways.
And And that's true, but that's
not the only case in which you
could multiply them both ways.
All we needed was that P, which
is the number of columns in B,
is equal to n, which is the
number of rows in A.
But it's not necessary that
those numbers are also the same
as D.
So for example, we could have A
be 3 by 2 and B be 2 by 3.
And there you could multiply
them both ways.
OK, so suppose A is 1, 0,
2,
1,
3, 0, whatever.
Make up some numbers.
This is a 3 by 2 matrix.
Suppose B is a 2 by 3 matrix, 0,
0,
1,
5, 4, 7.
That's a 2 by 3 matrix.
What is the shape of AB?
What is the shape of AB? 3.
Yeah.
3 by 3.
And what's the shape of BA?
You can see that by writing
them.
Again,
with this annotated notation,
you can put 2 by 3 next to B.
Next to A, you can put 3 by 2.
Because the inner dimensions are
the same, it's legal to
multiply.
But the dimensions or the shape
of the output will be the outer
dimensions.
So B A will be what?
What will the shape of B A be?
Yeah.
Two by two.
Awesome.
Which tells you,
even if both of them exist, so
even if both B A and A B exist,
they don't have to be the same
shape, which means they can't be
equal.
You can't have a three by three
matrix be the same thing as a
two by two matrix.
So even if a, b,
and b, a both exist,
they are not necessarily
the same shape.
Okay.
Now, what if they're both
square?
Let's find out.
Let's just make up an example.
So why don't we say A is one,
two, three, four,
and B is five, six, seven,
eight.
What is A times
B?
What's the first entry that is
the top left entry in A times B?
Yeah, close,
not exactly 15.
Yeah, 19.
How'd you get 19?
Good.
Remember we're taking dot
products of A's rows with the
first column of B,
right? So it'll be one times
two,
sorry,
one times five plus two times
seven.
Do we agree?
Okay, so we're gonna get a 19
there.
What's the next entry?
Well it's going to be still
we're working with the first
column of B and we're gonna dot
it with the second row of A.
So we're going to get 15 plus
28, which sounds like 43.
So those came from here.
And then the second two entries
are going to come from dotting
the second column of B with the
rows of A.
So what's the first entry going
to be? Looks like 6 plus 16,
which is 22.
Then the second will be 18 plus
32, which is 50.
I'll admit,
when you're dealing with two
matrices that are both n by n,
it gets confusing what dot
products you're supposed to
take, because it's actually
easier when they're not both
square, because there's only one
way it could work.
But here, you may accidentally
forget and take
the dot products of A's columns
with B's rows or something,
but that's not the same thing.
So this is what AB would be.
What about BA?
We don't need to do the whole
calculation.
Just one piece of it will tell
us they're not the same.
What is the top left entry in
BA?
How would we find it?
23.
How'd you get that?
It was like 1 times 5 plus 3
times 6.
And why are you doing that?
Well, it's because now B is the
left matrix and A is the right
matrix.
And how that's supposed to work
is you take dot products of the
rows of the first matrix with
the columns of the second.
So now we're dotting 5 6 with 1
3 5 plus 18 is 23,
which is not the same as 19
Which tells you a B and BA even
when the two matrices are square
don't need to be the same, okay
so in general a
B is not the same as BA
And something I subtly mentioned
is that when you're multiplying
two matrices,
the first one is called the left
matrix and the second one is
called the right matrix.
So often we will say things
like,
we will right multiply the
equation on both sides by
something,
or we will left multiply the
equation on both sides by
something, because those are
different.
You can't just say multiply the
order in which the operation
happens matters
And so say if we have an
equation and we need to perform
an operation to both sides of it
We need to specify well
How did we do that operation if
you multiply on the left on one
side and on the right on the
other? Well, you didn't actually
do the same thing to both sides
Okay
It's the same reason that you
know, if AV is a valid product
Well, then VA is not right the
shapes here don't match up
So this is left multiplying
by A.
Now,
you might ask, is there a way to
multiply a matrix and a vector
where the vector comes first?
And the answer is that it
requires the vector to be
written as a row vector.
And we'll see an example of that
very briefly at the end of today
before I get to
Yeah, I'll try and get to this.
So this is not valid
Okay, two quick examples I want
to introduce here the
first
Is this idea of an identity
matrix
To illustrate what's going on
here
Consider the matrix 1, 0, 0, 1.
And suppose I multiply it by
some arbitrary vector in R2,
AB.
What comes out?
What comes out of this
operation?
AB? Yeah.
It's the same vector AB.
Yeah, it's the same vector AB,
OK?
So multiplying AB by this matrix
1001 does nothing to
AB.
It comes out being the same.
So you should think of this
matrix 1001
as being the equivalent of
multiplying a number by 1.
Doesn't change its value.
And that neutral element in
whatever set of objects you're
working with is called the
identity element.
So one is called the
multiplicative identity when
you're working with real
numbers.
This matrix is called the
identity matrix, but there's not
just one identity matrix.
This is the identity matrix that
is two by two.
But you can imagine there's also
a three by three identity
matrix.
What does it look like?
You have to guess what the three
by three identity matrix looks
like.
And the way you describe
this is that the identity matrix
has ones on
the diagonal.
That's how you'd refer to the
placement of these ones here.
And the diagonal is made up of
all entries whose row number is
equal to their column number.
So for example,
this is row one,
column one.
This is row three,
column three.
And so the role of the identity
matrix is that it's that neutral
element that when you multiply
it by anything, you get back the
same result.
That's true for a matrix,
it's true for a vector.
So for example,
if I took the matrix 7, 4, 3, 2,
multiplied it by 1, 0, 0, 1,
whether I do that on the left or
on the right,
that is,
if the identity matrix appears
on the right, or if it appears
on the left,
I get back the same matrix I
started with.
And so something we will see
late next week is, what is the
inverse of a matrix?
The inverse of a matrix is just
another matrix
that when you multiply it by the
one you started with,
you get the identity matrix.
There's a bit more to it than
that,
because only square matrices
have inverses.
And that's partially because the
identity matrix is only a
concept for square matrices.
Why is that?
Why is there no not square
identity matrix?
Yeah.
It seems like you wouldn't be
able to have a proper diagonal
if it's not a square.
Exactly.
And it's also related to the
fact that the whole premise here
is that after multiplying this
vector in R2 by my matrix,
I also ended up with a vector in
R2.
But if the matrix isn't square,
then its shape changes after
getting multiplied by A.
OK, so in general,
if a is n by d,
and x is in R,
again, remind me what the shape
of x must be to multiply it by
a.
d,
it must be an Rd.
Then ax is in Rn.
And what
that means is unless A is a
square matrix,
then x's shape changes.
x and Ax have different shapes.
Do we agree?
OK.
What that means is if the whole
role of the identity matrix is
to be something that when you
multiply it by other things,
you get the same result back,
well then it inherently needs to
be square.
Otherwise, if I multiply it by a
vector, it would change its
shape, which means it can't be
the same thing after being
multiplied.
This is something we will
emphasize more next Thursday and
after the break,
this idea of thinking of the act
of multiplying the matrix by a
vector as transforming the
vector.
The default interpretation
you've probably built up in your
minds right now is what we are
doing is we're taking linear
combinations of the matrix's
columns.
And that's what we're going to
explore more on Tuesday.
But the other way to think about
this is,
you can think of x as being
passed into a function.
Or the thing we are doing to x
is we're just multiplying it by
a.
And as we will see,
that does,
in some cases,
some describable thing to x.
Like the kinds of things we will
say is that it rotates x, or it
stretches x, or it reflects it,
or it projects it.
These are all types of things
that a could do to x, depending
on what a is.
And we will study that more next
week.
The other thing I wanted to
briefly mention is the transpose
operation.
So suppose I have a 3 by 2
matrix A.
These components are 7, 0, 2,
1, 0, 1.
They don't need to have all
these zeros or else just put
something random here in pi.
The transpose of A,
think of it as like A's friend
who is defined by turning A's
rows into columns and
A's columns into rows and it
looks like this exponent T here.
Though it's not an exponent.
So if A is 3 by 2 What is A
transpose?
2 by 3.
Its first row is 702.
Its second row is A's second
column,
1 pi 1.
Do we agree?
Okay,
now the kind of thing we're
gonna study quite a bit next
week, and you're even gonna see
it in homework 5, is what does
the matrix A transpose A
contain? This is a very common
operation.
You're going to see it almost
every class for the rest of the
semester.
Something like A transpose A or
X transpose X.
This does something describable
in English.
Firstly, I guess here, what is
its shape going to be?
What is A transpose A shape
going to be?
Yeah.
Not quite.
It's a little tricky because A
transpose is being written
first, but here I'm seeing A
first.
Yeah, so indeed, it's going to
be 2 by 2.
Now, in English,
what does it contain?
It contains two rows and two
columns, but I more mean,
you could describe the entries
of A transpose A, of which there
will be four,
in English to someone who was in
this class but didn't come to
lecture today.
How could you describe them?
Awesome.
Is it going to be like the
elements square?
I see.
I think you have generally the
right idea.
Let me move them around so it's
a little more clear because
we're multiplying A transpose on
the left.
Though AA transpose is also a
valid thing.
What are the entries going to
be?
A dot product itself.
Yeah, it's the dot products of
all pairs of A's columns.
OK, let's check it out.
What's the first entry going to
be?
Well, it's going to be the first
row of A transpose dotted with
the first column of A.
But that's 702 dotted with 702.
What's the second thing going to
be?
Well, it's going to be still the
first column of A dotted with
the second row of A transpose.
Remember, the rows of A
transpose are just the columns
of A.
So down here,
I'm going to get 1 pi 1 dotted
with 702.
Then I'm going to take the
second column and dot it with
the first and second once again.
So what that tells you is these
entries are going to be the
same,
because they're both going to be
the dot product of A's first
column with A's second column.
They're both going to be 7 plus
2, which is
9.
Meanwhile, the top left entry is
going to be 49 plus 4, that's
going to be 53.
At the bottom right one, okay
this one's going to look stupid,
but it's going to be like pi
squared plus 2.
Are we clear on where these
numbers came from?
A transpose A contains the dot
products of
all pairs of A's columns.
We're going to use that a lot
this semester, so this is
something to internalize.
OK,
now if A transpose A contains
the dot products of pairs of A's
columns,
how do we get the dot products
of pairs of A's rows?
You had to guess.
Yeah?
Doing AA transpose.
Exactly, you do AA transpose.
Now,
an important fact to know about
the transpose operation is that
the transpose of a product, and
you can read more about this in
the notes,
flips the order of the product.
So AB transpose is equal to B
transpose A transpose.
And the last thing I wanted to
say before we fully run out of
time here is that you can write
the dot product of two vectors,
which remember requires them to
be column vectors,
in terms of this transpose.
How might you do that?
Let's just pretend I have the
vector 1, 2, 3 dotted with
7, 4, 7.
Can you think of how to write
this in terms of matrix
multiplication?
Without a dot product?
Because it seems like the matrix
multiplication has a dot product
built in.
You transpose v?
Close.
It's you translate, did you say
U or V?
Like,
U transpose.
Good, good, good.
What you can do is imagine
rotating the first vector
using the transpose.
And now you don't need a dot
product.
Remember, the dot product only
works between two column
vectors.
So it would be wrong to put a
dot there,
OK?
No dot.
But this is just regular matrix
multiplication.
I have a 1 by 3 matrix and a 3
by 1 matrix.
The result is 1 by 1 and it
comes from taking the dot
product of the first thing's
only row with the second thing's
only column, which is 7 plus 8
plus 21,
which is 30.
The number itself is not
important.
What I wanted to get at is this
is the transpose of u multiplied
by v.
Okay? And what that means is
there's lots of ways to write
the dot product.
There's u dot v,
there's u transpose v,
there's v transpose u,
and there's v dot u.
Those are all the same.
And so if you want a challenge
to ponder over the weekend,
see if you can simplify
the squared length of A x using
everything we've just discussed.
Okay,
that's it, sorry for going a
couple minutes over.
as usual I have office hours
after this, otherwise I'll see
you on Tuesday.
lost the end on the keyboard.
I don't know, I kind of locked
in, like, the fact that it says
something like, you know, I want
something like,
dot product,
whether,
like,
we expected that it would be
you, or you were the one that
was looking at it,
you're doing the same kind of
thing.
In general, you're right, that
it's not, like, we don't, like,
try to vent.
Good.
No good questions.
Take care.
To be accumulating more and more
chairs, I don't know, is it?
Oh yes,
I'm not sure if you'll have the
time today,
but please,
anyways,
from your teams,
Just in case you don't have the
time to finish what we started
last time,
thank you.